上集回顾 ...
既然你们开着沙滩车
Since you're in beach buggies,
你们将驶向沙滩
you will now drive to the beach
翻译
吃烧饼不掉芝麻 natas
北上到纳米比亚最北
at the northernmost point
和安哥拉的交界处
of Namibia, where it meets Angola.
翻译
InX Monica-卡
全程1600公里
It's 1,000 miles away.
校对
natas 顿顿 RN
我们一定要找到这条路
We have got to find this road.
在黑暗里这么开下去太冒险
This is not gonna be too clever in the dark.
时间轴
Monica-卡 natas RN
我一定会找到南十字星
Listen. I shall find the Southern Cross.
这主意真蠢
Oh, this is a bad idea!
我们把性命交在一只猩猩的手里
We are now trusting our lives
而这只猩猩又以为自己是帕特里克 穆尔
to an orangutang who thinks he's Patrick Moore.
整整24小时 又冰冷又悲惨
24 hours of cold, misery,
结果又回到原点
to achieve exactly nothing.
真的一事无成
I mean, it is exactly nothing.
海水涨过来了
Oh, it's coming in!
这是我走过的最诱人的沙漠
This is the best desert I've ever been to.
我勒个槽
Holy shit!
它实际是个庞大的橙色杀人机器
What it actually is is a big, orange killing engine.
妈呀
- Jesus!
老天爷
Oh, my God!
求求你 开上去吧
Please make it! Please!
真的需要找到路了 这可很严肃了
Just need to find a road now. This is not funny any more.
不想再在沙漠里过夜
I don't want another night in the desert.
谢天谢地
Oh, my God.
可以向东 可以向西
I could go east, I could go west.
不管去哪儿都有路
Whichever way you go, it goes somewhere.
通向自由的大路
Yes! It is the road to freedom.
什么鬼东西
What the hell was that?
我在开的 至少在试着开的 真是阿波罗13号
What I'm driving here, or attempting to drive, is Apollo 13.
等到早上 我才把伤势惨烈的座驾蹭到温得和克
It was morning by the time I nursed my wounded car into Windhoek,
而我吃好睡好的败类同事们
and my well-rested colleagues were full of admiration
对我的壮举充满了崇拜
for how I'd pulled off such a feat.
-这是你的第一方案么  -怎么了
-Is that the first thing you thought of? - What?
就拆了一个洞 这能有啥用
Tear a hole in it. What's that gonna do?
我要够着散热器那的引气活门 在那儿
I needed to get to the bleed valve on the radiator, which is there.
-继续说  -这还不算 还有更倒霉的
- Is it? - And, to make life doubly difficult...
我把我眼镜片给踩了
...I trod on my spectacles.
也太杯具了 单眼兽当修车师傅
That is tragic, trying to fix it with one lens.
我试着修车 而且我只会闭右眼
I was trying to fix it. And the only eye I can close is this eye.
-左眼闭不上么  -闭不上
-You can't close your left eye? -I can't close my left eye.
你怎么不把眼镜倒过来 那样右眼就能用了
Why didn't you put them on upside down? You'd have the lens over the other eye.
神逻辑
That is logic there.
说得有理
Oh, yeah
-好吧 上路吧 今天要赶路  -慢着
- Come on, let's go. We've got a lot to do. - JEREMY: No!
我们目前唯一得到的教训就是
The one thing we have established now is that,
除了首都温得和克
with the exception of Windhoek,
纳米比亚的土地步步维艰
which is the capital, Namibia is a tough and arduous place.
-有理  -你买了地图吗
- Yeah. - Have you bought maps?
你有任何宿营设施吗
- No. - Have you got tenting equipment of any sort?
除了躺沙子上 你想好了沙漠露营地吗 都没有
Have you got somewhere to sleep other than the desert floor? No.
要我说 今天我们养精蓄锐
So why don't we, today, get prepared
为了下段旅程 一大段旅程做准备
for the next leg of the - big leg of the journey?
-好主意  -那就这样定了
- That is a good idea. We'll do that. - That's not a bad idea.
我们给自己奖励购物一天
We'll grant ourselves a day of... shopping. Mm.
不过首先 请容我一刻
First of all, would you permit me to chisel some of the cheddar
把裤衩里捂出来的百虫千菌清一清
that has grown in my underpants away?
你别在这儿干
Well, not here.
在刮干净我的器官后
Having de-cheesed my body parts,
我们去搞一些必要的物资
we headed out to get the necessary supplies.
问题是 如果我们用网眼布材料
The thing is, if we go mesh,
网眼挡太阳但是不挡光
it'll keep the sun off but it won't keep the light out.
有光睡不了懒觉 而且它重1.5公斤 但
That will wake us up early. That's 1.5 kilograms. But--
哈蒙德 在我们血拼之前你一定要明白
Hammond, the first thing you need to know before we start shopping in here
我和船长俩人说算
is James and I are in charge.
对不住 不过你不说算
Well... - JAMES: Sorry, he's right.
你们做不了主意 因为你们对宿营一无所知
No, you're not. You don't know anything about camping.
-正因为如此  -那么干嘛要拿主意
- JAMES, JEREMY: Exactly. - How does that make you in charge?
因为我们清楚宿营很糟糕
Because we know it's all terrible.
如果你说了算 我们最后得会在小迷彩三角袋里过夜
If we leave it to you, we'll all end up sleeping in small green triangles.
你对野外宿营的概念是在湖畔
The camping you know about is in the Lake District,
故意过悲惨野人生活
where you deliberately make yourself miserable.
对不起 不过他一点没错
I'm sorry, he's right.
依我所见
It is possible, I think,
只有才华和金钱
with a bit of ingenuity and money,
才能让露营至少可以忍受
to make tenting bearable.
童子军哈蒙德并不认同
Richard Baden-Hammond disagreed,
所以我们就地解散
so we went our separate ways.
正确 错误
Correct, incorrect.
-没错 -同意吗
- Exactly. - Do you agree?
-我这有个更正确的  -赞
- But I'd go even more correct. - Oh, yes!
完美 在沙子上这样卷开
Perfect. Roll it out on the desert floor...
像到家了一样
...you're home.
詹姆斯 我找到酷彩锅了
Oh, James! Le Creuset!
哈蒙德会恨死这玩意 它比帐篷还重
See, Hammond would hate this, because this weighs more than a tent.
-确实重  -重很多
- Which it does, actually. - A lot more.
酷彩锅由铸铁制成 很重
-高重量 高质量  -真理
- And it weighs more because it is a quality item. - Exactly.
便携泥铲
Pocket trowel.
便携香皂
Pocket soap.
这才像话
Here we go.
-意面匙  -好主意
- Pasta spoon. - Yeah, good idea.
这个开瓶器有点.. 太轻了
I find that bottle opener a bit... lightweight.
我们要找更烧钱的
Yeah, more expensive is what we're looking for.
船长 过来看
You see, look at this, James.
哈蒙德会把这种破玩意儿当成椅子
This is the sort of thing Hammond would think is a chair.
这是必备 一个灶炉就搞定了
Ooh! That's all you need. That's your whole... stove.
这就够了
That's it.
-这是燃气灶吧  -应该是
- Is it gas? It is, isn't it? - I presume so.
两个灶炉 能塞个小鸡了 野鸡也行
For two, you could get a small chicken in there, or... a pheasant.
差不多了
We're getting there now.
可以这样折叠
So that folds down to that.
不错
Yeah.
第二天清晨 我们重新上路
The next morning, we headed out once more,
詹姆斯和我采买的
with the camping gear James and I had bought
露营物资随后跟车
bringing up the rear.
购买物资之余
And besides stocking up with essentials,
我和哈蒙德还在首都休整时改装了车
Hammond and I had used our day off in Windhoek to modify our cars.
为了改善发动机过热 我装了个集风进气铲
To solve my overheating problems, I've fitted a ram-air scoop,
开车时 会把凉风铲进散热器
which shovels refreshing, cooling air into the radiator as I go along.
而且你可能看到了 我装了一个风翼
And, as you may have noticed, I've fitted a spoiler.
我的沙滩车对我来说唯一的不足
My only complaint, really, about my beach buggy
就是在3档和4档动力不够
was its lack of performance in third and fourth gears.
没法给发动机加动力 不想给引擎压力
Couldn't up power from the engine and I don't want to stress it,
不过我可以给车减肥
so I could lighten it.
我把这里的顶架去掉 扔掉了副驾驶座椅
I've stripped away the superstructure here and the passenger seat,
不必要的该删就删
anything spare.
结果就是 这辆车轻了三四十公斤
That means this car is 30-40 kilos lighter than it was before.
杰里米 你的车怎么长出了土绿的八字胡
Jeremy, why has your car sprouted a green moustache?
是个风翼 为了给车头增加下压力
Well, it's a spoiler for added downforce at the front end,
后置引擎车很需要
which you need in a rear-engine vehicle.
这辆车现在过弯能力惊人
This thing will be unbelievable through the corners now,
不骗你
it really will.
和保时捷911没两样
Like a 911.
我跟你说
And I tell you what,
就算你的超轻沙滩车
even with your new lightweight buggy,
和我现在的座驾相比 也只能后面吃灰
you're no match for what I've got here this morning.
不好意思 我的车更快
Yeah, I'm sorry, mate. This is quicker.
-瞎说  -才没
- It is not. - It is.
好吧 哈蒙德 我向你挑战
Right, Richard Hammond, I challenge you to a race.
战就战 谁怕谁  大白痴
OK, you're on. Idiot.
我们找个赛道 去赛车
We shall find a race track and we shall do racing.
你们玩你们的 我才不赛车
Well, you carry on. I'm not doing any racing.
一点意义也没有
That's utterly pointless.
在市郊
On the outskirts of the city,
我们找到了一个不错的赛道
we found a rather excellent circuit
在这里 我们可以跑圈计时
where we could do timed laps,
詹姆斯可以玩玩他新买的吸尘器
and James could try out his new vacuum cleaner.
爽歪歪
Oh, yes.
-准备好没  -不行
- Are you ready? - No.
-你干嘛  -要等水温和胎压
- Why not? - Temperatures and pressures.
这可是赛道神器 看看它
This is a racing machine. Look at it.
不过是塑料沙滩车 停在V8旁边
It's a plastic beach buggy parked near a V8.
-还有空力套件  -少来
- With aero. - Really?
各就各位
- In...
.3 2 1 起步
..three, two, one, go!
得让我挂上档
Yeah, I'm gonna do it in gear.
-再试试  -让我再试试
- Give it a shot. - I'm gonna try that.
-各就各位  -不行 油门卡死了
- In-- - No! Throttle's jammed.
-还是卡着的  -各就各位
- Jammed. - In--
停 这破油门
No! You can keep saying "in"
你说 各就各位 说到天黑也没用
till the cows come home. The throttle...
3 2 1 走起
Three, two, one, begin!
怎么停下了
Why... Why have you stopped?
油门又收不回来了
The throttle may have gone a bit open.
油门完全报废
My throttle is totally broken.
-话说回来 哈蒙德  -啥事
- Anyway, Hammond... - Yeah?
任何起步能前轮飞起的车
Any car which can wheelie off the line...
击败你都完全没问题
is going to be able to beat yours, and would have done.
不好意思 打断你
So... Sorry.
你是说 你的车刚开跑
You're saying because your car started,
没跑50米就坏了
well, 50 yards away over there,
前轮飞起 失控 砸下来
wheelied, was uncontrollable, slammed back down
趴窝 这就是赛道神器么
and broke itself, it's the best on the track?
没错
Yes.
长知识了 真实用 多亏这比赛
Well, much learned. Really useful. Glad we did it.
等杰里米把不断出状况的车修好
With Jeremy's endlessly troublesome car fixed again,
我们没收了詹姆斯的戴森 继续向北
we scooped up James' Dyson and continued northwards
戴森 吸尘器品牌
向安哥拉边境前进
towards the finish line at the border with Angola.
一路上 风顺 路平 不同寻常地安静
The going was smooth and easy and eerily quiet,
这就奇怪了
which begged a question.
据说纳米比亚是世界上开车最危险的地方
Now, apparently, Namibia is the most dangerous place in the world to drive.
这里的人均事故率比其它地方都高
There are more accidents per head then anywhere else,
而且 在青年人口中
and car accidents are the first
车祸是造成死亡最大的诱因
and most common cause of death in young adults.
为什么 这怎么可能
How? How can that be so?
你看 这里万里无人
I mean... the place is empty.
在英国 平均每平方公里有250-260人
In Britain, there are 250-260 people for every square kilometre.
在这里 平均只有2人
Here... it's two.
两个人
Two!
与这相比 澳大利亚的荒漠像是摩纳哥一样热闹
This makes the Australian outback look like Monaco.
有猴子
Monkey! Monkey!
屁眼超大 你们看到了吗
Huge anus! Did you see that thing's anus?
与此同时
I, however, was not thinking
我想的不是人口数和猴臀
about population statistics or monkeys' bottoms.
我只是庆幸终于开在了平路上
I was just happy to be on a smooth surface
而且车里不再遍布灰尘
in a car that wasn't filled with dust.
轻松上阵
I shall relax...
风景迷人
...with the lovely view.
不幸地是 几里路之后
Sadly, though, a few miles later...
嗷嗷嗷 我的蛋蛋啊
Ow! Ow! Oh, my nuts! Ow!
别闹了
Stop it!
詹姆斯梅
James May?
我能听到 我太不爽了
Yes, I can hear you, but it's very uncomfortable
我的车也 说坏就坏了
and my car has... has cut out.
詹姆斯很幸运
Mercifully for James,
我们开到了野生动物保护区
we eventually arrived at a game reserve,
我们决定这里是理想的
which we decided would be an ideal place
过夜宿营地
to set up camp for the night.
这就够了
That's what we need.
一边是哈蒙德搭建帆布小破屋
As Hammond built his canvas hovel...
我和詹姆斯期待着更文明的夜晚
...James and I were looking forward to a more civilised evening
就在我们顺带买来的管家
in the tents we'd bought,
为我们建起来
and which had been erected
过夜帐篷里
by the butler we'd also bought.
多谢 乔瓦尼
Thank you, Giovanni.
把你衬衫塞裤子里 这不是房车旅行
Tuck your shirt in, man! It's not a bloody caravan site.
我在想 晚餐
Erm... I'm just thinking, dinner.
我先去换件衣服行不行
Mm. Do you mind if I get changed?
我也要去冲个澡
- No, exactly. I'm gonna have a shower. - Mm.
-去泡个澡吧  -真心赞
- Or I may have a bath, actually. - Why not?
乔瓦尼 去把热水准备了
Giovanni, could you run the baths?
据说这家餐厅还有牡蛎
Apparently, this place has got oysters.
-是么 在这还有  -可说是呢 多厉害
- Really? Here? - Yeah. I know, it's extraordinary.
谁能想到咧
Who knew?
来共进晚餐吗
Are you coming for some dinner?
你什么意思 共进晚餐 我都在这儿做好了
What do you mean, "Coming for dinner"? I'm cooking here.
那里有一家餐厅
There's a restaurant just down there.
-餐厅  -没错 就在前面
- A restaurant? - Yeah, just down there.
我不想去
I don't want to go.
我在这里正经露营
I'm cooking this. I'm doing it properly, camping.
-你就来 -餐后我来找你们
- Well, come and-- - I'll join you after dinner.
随你吧
Whatever.
他整个一土老汉
He's such a peasant, isn't he?
太不可思议了
It's just unbelievable.
晚饭时
That evening in the restaurant,
哈蒙德并没有加入我们
Hammond never did join us.
不过我和詹姆斯却不孤单
But James and I were not short of company.
看 有犀牛 真犀牛哎
Oh, look, there's rhinos! There's actual rhinos!
它们的牛角已经被拔了
And they've been dehorned.
为了防止偷猎者射杀犀牛
They've had to take its horn out
才把牛角摘除
to stop poachers shooting it.
不过你知道偷猎者现在会干出什么事来吗
But you know what the poachers are doing?
他们也会杀牛角摘除过的犀牛
They shoot the dehorned ones,
他们会跟踪一只犀牛 跟踪几天
because if they track for a couple of days, a rhino,
如果发现犀牛没有角 就把它射掉
and then it's got no horn, they shoot it,
以后就不用再跟踪同一只犀牛了 节省时间
and then they'll never track it again, so it saves time.
你知道现在犀牛角什么价吗
Do you know how much you get for a rhino horn now?
-在黑市场上吗  -对 比如在越南
- On the... On the market? - Yeah, in Vietnam.
我敢猜是一大笔钱
I'm guessing it's a lot.
32万美金
$320,000.
-比金条还值钱  -老天爷啊
- So that's more expensive than gold. - Good God.
就连这只犀牛上还留下的那个小瘤
Even the nub that's left that he's got is still worth,
我估计也值几千美金
I don't know, thousands of dollars.
我正要说 不论多细致地除角
I was gonna say, no matter how carefully you dehorn it,
还是会有一点遗留在鼻子里面
there's still horn going down into its nose.
-这太令人寒心了  -可说是的
- JEREMY: That's such a tragedy, that, you know. - JAMES: Yeah.
我想我们既然来了 就做点贡献
I want to do something about this while we're here.
一定可以想出解决办法的
I'm sure we could come up with something.
一定可以
I'm sure we could.
第二天清晨 天一亮我就被征兵
RICHARD: The next morning, I woke to find I'd been recruited
进了克拉克森和梅犀牛保护小队
into the Clarkson and May Rhino Protection Squad.
他们俩居然一口咬定
They were even convinced that our beach buggies
我们的沙滩车是跟踪偷猎者的首选车辆
would be ideal for tracking the poachers.
不可否认 他们说的犀牛问题有道理
I can't deny, they do have a point about the whole rhino thing.
简直荒谬
It is ridiculous.
在非洲 平均每天都有两只犀牛被射杀
Two rhinos killed every day in Africa by poachers,
被卖给黑市 因为有人迷信
and then sold to a market that believes it's a cure for cancer,
犀牛角能治癌症 阳痿 甚至宿醉
impotence, even hangovers.
不过要正面解决这个大问题
But are we necessarily the right men
我们几个是最佳人选么
to tackle it head-on in the field?
在超市里捐献个一块钱
Wouldn't we be better just popping a £1 coin in a jar
让专家来解决问题 岂不是更有效
and letting somebody who knows what they're doing solve it?
从昨天住宿的地方
Well, I've got a tranquilizer gun
我拿了支麻醉枪
from the place where we were last night, but...
但我找不到谁能当靶子
...I can't see anyone to shoot.
估计偷猎者是不会用大路
Figuring that the poachers probably didn't use the main road,
于是我们驶进了树丛里寻找
we went off to look in the bush.
那边怎么样
What about over there?
没有偷猎者
No poachers.
这里有轮胎记
Tyre marks.
可能会是偷猎者
It may be some poacher.
不对
Oh, no, wait.
百路驰轮胎 这是詹姆斯的胎记
BF Goodriches. This is James May.
你给我听着 我们这事儿太蠢了
Just so you know, this is stupid.
怎么蠢了
What's stupid?
你怎么能认出来偷猎者
How would you recognise a poacher when you saw one?
-就算你找到了 又能把他怎么样  -射他
- And when you find one, what are you gonna do? - Shoot him.
这次旅程唯一的目的
All we're doing on our journey
只是开三辆沙滩车到安哥拉边境
is driving three beach buggies to the Angolan border.
-没错  -这对人类社会没什么贡献
- Yeah. - Which doesn't further the cause of humanity.
-说得对  -这么转悠着就有贡献了么
- Exactly. - And this does, does it?
哈蒙德 我们有一天时间 给我们24小时
We've got a day, Hammond. Give us 24 hours.
就一天 之后我们保证重新再上路
24 hours. Then, I promise, we'll get back on the road.
持怀疑态度的队友让步之后
JEREMY: Once our sceptical colleague had agreed,
我决定改变策略
I decided to change tack,
放弃陆路 从空中搜索
abandon the cars and search from the air,
借用些沙漠滑翔帆伞设备
using some beach-front parasailing equipment.
-杰里米  -啥事
- Jeremy? - Yes?
如果我们活不回来 你记住 我恨死你了
If we don't make it, please know that I hate you.
连一丝风都没有 别犯傻了
There's not a breath of wind, so don't be stupid.
哎呀 我的降落伞
Oh, my parachute's been...
-不妙  -拜拜了您呐
- Oh, hello! - Goodbye.
屎啊
Shit!
搞栽了
That's not worked at all.
好吧 我不敢这么玩命了
OK. Right, I'm not gonna do that.
很显然 我的策略太危险了
Clearly, my solution was too dangerous for us,
于是我们把乔瓦尼送了上去
so we sent Giovanni up instead.
看 他飞远了 马上就会坠下来死掉
Look, he's going over there. He's gonna crash and die.
-他只是被风吹歪了  -而且要吹掉下来了
- No, he's been blown a bit sideways but-- - And downwards.
他自己没同意吧
He didn't sign up for this, did he?
乔瓦尼没找到任何偷猎者
Giovanni failed to spot any poachers,
所以我们让他别再胡搞了
so we told him to stop messing about
回到营地里给我们倒酒
and get back to camp to pour some drinks,
这时 我们集体反思
whilst we had a rethink.
我们所有的计划都没成功
Everything we've tried has gone wrong.
承认失败 继续前行吧
So let's accept it now and move on.
抓紧赶路
We can go.
不干
No.
我估计偷猎者只会在晚上出来偷猎
I think the poachers only go out at night.
你丫真狠
Oh, for God's sake.
我们等太阳下山了
We'll let the sun set,
找来先进的战术装备
get some tactical kit.
-手持步枪  -来玩吧 哈蒙德
- Rifles. - Come on, Hammond.
你说给我们24小时 之后才要我们缴枪呢
You gave us 24 hours before you took our guns and badges.
-他的确说过  -行吧
- He did. -  OK.
再整几瓶啤的 然后就去耍
I think a couple more beers, head out there.
赞
I agree.
-耐心点 等到天黑  -对的
- Let it get dark. Be patient. - Yes.
-捕猎者都需要耐心  -当然
- Hunters are patient, aren't they? - Exactly.
等到一片漆黑
JEREMY: Once darkness had fallen,
我们开始行动
we got kitted out
手持麻醉枪 身穿武装衣
with tranquilizer guns and tactical kit
带着没信心的哈蒙德
and headed back into the bush
重新回到了树丛中
with a very unsure Richard in tow.
我不是不想阻止偷猎
I mean, I'd like to stop poachers,
不过晚上在这里 偷猎者和狮子的比例是多少
but out here at night, what is the poacher-to-lion ratio?
两者中 我更会遇到哪一个
What am I more likely to find?
必要的策略是跟随犀牛脚印
What you have to do is look for rhino tracks,
因为偷猎者也会这样跟踪犀牛
cos that's what the poachers will be following.
真是一生中做过的最男子汉的事情
Literally the most manly thing I've ever done.
伟大旅程爷们版 血肉横飞没人管
Grand Tour for men, splashing all over.
-我勒个槽  -你个王八蛋
- JEREMY: Bloody hell! - RICHARD: You stupid bastards!
我被击中了
Someone's shot me!
哈蒙德
RICHARD: Hammond? Hammond?
哈蒙德 收到请回复
Hammond?
你个大猩猩
Clarkson, you moron.
哈蒙德
Hammond?
好吧 该诚实就得诚实
Right, well, I have to be honest,
昨天一整天都在浪费时间
yesterday was a total waste of time.
什么事都没办成
We achieved nothing.
唯一成了的就是射伤了哈蒙德
All we did achieve was we seem to have wounded Mr Hammond,
而且今天早上 怎么叫他都叫不醒
who er... well, we couldn't wake him up this morning at all.
我们今天实在要有长路要赶
And because we needed to get going, we've a long way to go,
于是不得不临场发挥
we've had to improvise.
搞什么鬼
What the (BLEEP)?
这他妈怎么回事
What the (BLEEP) is this?
混蛋
You bastards!
而在地面上
Back on the ground,
我和詹姆斯也困难重重
James and I had our own problems.
老天爷啊
- Oh, God!
这段路一定会帮我治愈
This is very good for the gravel rash
昨天帆伞事故得的皮疹
that I got... during my parachute accident yesterday.
好疼
Oh, that hurts.
真希望能下场小雨
What we could really do with is a rain shower
把这些灰尘压下去
to dampen this dust down.
看起来可能性不大
JAMES: I think it's unlikely.
看起来不像是有要下雨的迹象
Yeah, there's no evidence that rain is on its way, I would say.
过了一会儿 对讲机里说
JEREMY: Soon, word came over the radio
哈蒙德马上会和我们重新回合
that Hammond was on his way to rejoin us...
而且他的情绪可能不算最好
...and that he wasn't in the best of moods.
搞什么搞
What was that?
你们什么意思
What was that about?
-我们不想把你落后面  -你又起不来
- We didn't want to leave you behind. - You wouldn't wake up.
啊 对 你不想把我落了
No, obviously, you didn't want to leave me behind,
所以你们做了合逻辑的事
so you did the logical thing,
趁我没醒 把我绑在直升机下面
which is suspend me from a helicopter whilst asleep.
-没错啊  -别人也会这么做 是么
- Yes. - Most people would arrive at the same conclusion.
当然不是 你们是拿我找乐子
No, you didn't! You were having a laugh!
你不知道刚才有多颠
Do you realise how rough the first road was
而你不用开啊
that you haven't had to drive on?
而你能乘直升机 我们不行啊
And you got a helicopter ride, which we haven't had.
我要是从那玩意里摔出来
You wouldn't be laughing and sniggering so much
你们就不会在这嘻嘻哈哈了
if I'd fallen out of that thing, as I could have done.
恩 那样是不可笑
Well, it wouldn't be funny.
也不对 只是不好玩而已
No, it just wouldn't be interesting.
保护犀牛计划惨败之后
JEREMY: With the rhino fiasco behind us,
我们继续原来的任务
we got back to the job in hand...
抵达安哥拉边境
...which was to reach the Angolan border,
以此来证明 沙滩车
and therefore prove that beach buggies
是无所不能的绝佳机器
are brilliant go-anywhere machines
而非孩子气的小玩具
and not just frivolous toys.
但今天 这个理论将受到严峻考验
Today, however, that theory would be seriously tested.
老天爷啊
Oh, for God's sake!
啊 震到蛋碎啊
Ow! Christ on a bike!
我不想承认啊 但我好羡慕哈蒙德
I hate to admit this, but I'm jealous of Hammond.
我也想在车上有那套避震
I wish I'd fitted that suspension on my car.
这车全天都这样怎么可能扛得住
How is this car gonna stand up to this punishment all day?
好吧 既然这是我自己设计的车
Well, since it had been designed by me
零部件也都有40岁高龄了
and made from 40-year-old components,
这问题的答案很伤感地在意料之中
the answer was depressingly predictable.
你看 发电机已经从铰链上掉下来了
The alternator, as you can see, has come off its hinge.
这里应该有个螺栓的 掉了
The bolt's supposed to go in there and it's just come off.
那螺栓 应该在后面 160公里的某处
And the bolt, well, that's somewhere back there, 100 miles.
好了 我的发电机现在靠螺丝起子挂着
So, my alternator is now held on with a screwdriver
我亲手锤进去的
that I've hammered into place.
效果非凡
And we're running well.
我真有点束手无策了
Oh. I don't know what I'm gonna do about it,
风扇皮带没了
but I don't have a fan belt on there.
又有问题了
I've got a problem.
才走了8公里 又掉了个风扇皮带
Another five miles, another fan belt.
我要两件紧身衣才行
I'm gonna need a pair of tights.
不光我这样
And it wasn't just me.
这里 这里 点火开关 都检查过了
I've been through all of that, all of that, the ignition cut-out switch.
但机器就像中邪一样
I've got some weird gremlin.
这路要把车给拆了
JEREMY: This road is just shaking these cars to pieces.
当然了 杰里米一心认定
JAMES: Naturally, Jeremy decided that the only way
唯一能让车保持完整的方法
of keeping his car in one piece
就是开得飞快
was to drive very quickly.
我的理想速度是2800转
My optimum speed is 2,800 rpm,
这是唯一工作的仪表了
that being my only dial, really.
这样 我就能跳过坑洼了
That way, I'm skipping over the top of the ridges.
不幸的是 这速度下
Unfortunately, at this speed,
我的V8每50公里
my V8 was emptying the petrol tank
就把油箱喝干了
every 31 miles.
而我们在露营店里忘记买的一样东西
And one of the items we'd forgotten to buy at the camping shop
就是漏斗
was a funnel.
好了 风小了点 来吧
Right, wind's dropped. Here we go.
给我喝
Drink!
绝对安全
This is completely safe.
有些汽油 嗷我的好姑姑诶
Some of the petrol is... Oh, my giddy aunt!
路况越来越糟
The roads are getting worse.
虽然路途艰辛
Even though the going was appalling...
但沙滩车们 很神奇的
...the beach buggies, amazingly,
多多少少还保持完整
were, more or less, still in one piece.
不过 随着坑洼不断
However, as the relentless pounding wore on,
这话在詹姆斯那就没用了
the same could not be said of James.
老天啊
Oh, my God!
讲真我骨头都要碎了
Honestly, my bones are going to shatter.
我受够了
I've had enough of this.
我正试着把前避震调软
What I'm doing is I'm trying to soften up the front suspension,
然后把轮胎也弄软
and I'm gonna soften the tyres as well.
我在这里动动手脚
I've done quite a bit under here.
然后把轮胎里的气放掉些
Now I'm going to let a bit of air out of the tyres.
效果立竿见影啊
JAMES: This made a huge difference.
简直垃圾
This is rubbish!
别颠了
Stop!
但根本停不下来
But it didn't stop.
一路颠着
It went on...
颠着
...and on.
那天 我开了560公里
That day, I did 350 miles,
每公里都浸淫着痛苦
and every single one of them was filled with pain,
交织着灰尘与不幸
dust and misery.
所以 第二天早上
And that's why , the following morning,
我想到了个激进的计划
I came up with a radical plan.
别在路上开 开在路旁
Don't drive on the road, drive near it.
我在路旁开了一小段
I did a bit alongside the road.
虽然只有半公里
Admittedly only half a kilometre,
但简直天差地别
but it was bliss by comparison.
就像开在新铺装好的银石赛道上
It was like driving on a freshly resurfaced Silverstone.
我们不需要离开路好几公里
We don't have to stray miles from it.
我同意 这会很纯 我们会变成骷髅骨架的
I agree, that would be foolish, cos we could just end up as skeletons.
不过 说真的 我痛苦极了
But, honestly, it's agony in mine.
头颈疼 头疼 恨死了
I've got neck ache, headache. I hate it.
好 我跟你讲 哈蒙德 我为什么喜欢他的计划
Right, I tell you what, Hammond. I tell you why I like his idea.
如果是平地越野 我们会更舒服
If it is smooth off-road, it's more comfortable for us.
如果情况糟糕 我们就怪他
If it's hopeless out there, we can blame him.
很公平
Fair enough.
决定之后 我们就离开路面
JEREMY: With that settled, we left the road
一路开进船长高速
and set out on Highway May.
肯定詹姆斯一点 确实比路上平顺
I'll give James one thing, it is smoother than the road,
但我速度只有5
but I am doing 3 mph.
我说 我喜欢越野 真的
I mean, yeah, I like off-roading, I do,
但 这真的不快啊 对吧
but... this isn't exactly quicker, is it?
可惜 过了一小会
JEREMY: Sadly, a short while later,
我们连平顺路面都没了
we didn't even have smooth going for us.
哦 漂亮
Oh, spiffing.
詹姆斯 我希望你开心啊
James, I hope you're happy with this.
要这都比原来好 那之前得要多糟
How bad must it have been for him if this is better?
啊 老天 这人怎么这么蠢
Oh, God al-bloody-mighty! What an idiot that man is!
是啊 这可没那么颠了
Yeah, this is a lot less bumpy.
老天
Oh, Christ!
这更好 真的么
Is this better? Really?
别叫了
Stop moaning!
哈蒙德 我整个油门都掉下来了
JEREMY: Hammond, my entire throttle assembly has disintegrated.
我不懂 但我确定这路脱不了干系
RICHARD: I can't see why. I'm sure this is all helping it.
路上绝对没问题的
JEREMY: Perfectly all right on the road.
是啊 我就不懂为啥越来越多人
Yeah, I don't know why more people
不把车开在公路上
don't drive their cars on the road.
别让这风景给你的设计失误背锅
Stop blaming your failures on the scenery.
他胯部的每根骨头
Every bone in his crotch...
我都想打碎
that's what I'm gonna break.
每 一 根
Every single one of them.
接着 让人难以置信的是
And then, if it were at all possible,
船长旅行社的路线更糟了
May Tours got even worse.
天啊 这灰
Oh! Oh, God! The dust! Agh!
我们是开到星际迷航的特效里了么
What is this Star Trek special effect we've arrived in?
天啊
Oh, my God!
我是游过了灰啊 真的是游过去的
I am swimming through dust. I'm actually swimming in it.
天啊 天啊
Oh, dear, oh, dear!
我们开进的东西叫做浮土
JAMES: We had driven into something called fesh fesh,
像滑石粉一样细的沙
a sand as fine as talcum powder.
哦草
Oh, shite!
这让Ali G更怒了
And this had made Ali G even more cross.
Ali G 由Sacha Baron Cohen虚构的喜剧人物 易怒 短视 成见深
我什么都看不到了 我得要
I can't see a bloody thing now. I've got to...
都没法找到詹姆斯然后宰了他了
I can't even find James May to kill him.
好了 发动机炸锅了 我困住了
JEREMY: OK, the engine's boiling and I'm stuck.
电子系统全乱套了
All my electrics have gone haywire
我 还在试着把车子发动 电池不行了
My... It's still trying to turn the motor over. The battery's dead.
你困住了么 詹姆斯
Are you stuck, James?
呃
Er...
我猜我困住了
I think I'm stuck.
干得漂亮 詹姆斯
Well done, James.
你走了大家都好
Improved our lot no end.
所以情况就是
So the situation is...
哈蒙德的车坏了 你困住了
Hammond has broken his car, you're stuck,
我的过热了
and mine's overheated.
我们是不是该说 詹姆斯 你的主意蠢透了
Are we going to say, James, that your idea was stupid?
是蠢透了
It was stupid.
连固执中士都承认战败
JEREMY: With even Sergeant Stubborn admitting defeat,
是时候认输了
it was time to throw in the towel.
所以我们把自己安排妥当 在河里洗了个澡
So we got ourselves sorted out, got a wash in the river
回到了路上
and headed back to the road.
你瞧 新烫好的亚麻衬衫
There you go. Freshly ironed linen shirt
还有和我沙滩车同款肩章
with epaulettes that matches my beach buggy.
乔瓦尼烫的
Ironed by Giovanni.
不管别的
Despite everything,
我们的沙滩车的1600公里旅途
our beach buggies had covered 750 miles
已经完成了1200公里
of our 1,000-mile journey,
而我们现在已经深入北纳米比亚的
and we were now well into the tribal regions
原始部落领地
of northern Namibia...
教科书般的非洲
...which is picture-book Africa.
言语已经无法形容这里的美了
Well, this is all a bit too beautiful for words along here.
瞧瞧这
Look at this.
纳米比亚部落 我喜欢
Tribal Namibia, I like it.
我们所在的地方 完全是
Where we are now, it's genuinely...
怎么说好 未受玷污的
Well, what would you say, "unspoiled"? Yeah.
人们过着和数千年以前
People do live the lives
完全一样的生活
they've led here for thousands of years.
不好
Oh, no!
不好 我车不行了
Oh, no! I'm dying!
烦人的是 詹姆斯梅的远足
Annoyingly, the James May excursion
对我车的损坏远糟于我预期
had caused more damage than I'd realised.
噢 现在这里卡住了
Oh, now this is stuck on.
蠢货
Oh, bugger.
接着 代替道路救援服务的
Then, instead of the breakdown-recovery service,
一群无上装妇女来了
some topless ladies arrived...
你们好
RICHARD: Hello.
这让我不知道该把视线往哪放
...which made knowing where to look a bit difficult.
呃 全心干活啊 理查德
Erm... Concentrate on the job, Richard.
这不寻常啊
This is unusual.
和平时道路救援相比的话
I mean, normally the AA would have done.
谢谢啦
Thank you!
真棒
Very good.
哦还没完
Oh, there's more.
我也在休养船长旅行社造成的创伤
JEREMY: I, too, was nursing wounds as a result of May Tours.
我好像
I do seem to have lost...
缺了一个缸
...one of my cylinders somehow.
我在开V7啊
I'm driving a V7.
基本上 这就是喷天万能车了
Basically, this is now Spitty Spitty Bang Bang.
Chitty Chitty Bang Bang 飞天万能车 英国小说/电影
所以 在午餐休息时 理查德和我
So, at the lunch stop, Richard and I decided
决定开始报复梅先生
to get our revenge on Mr May.
怎么啦
What?
你... 放哪儿去了
You've put... Where's...
太糟心了
That is disturbing.
更糟心的是 我的原版古董大众档把
What's annoying is, what have you done
你把它怎么样了
with my original vintage VW gear knob?
不 这是好消息
Ah, well, no, good news on that.
乔瓦尼已经把你的原厂档把
Giovanni has posted your original gear lever
寄到你伦敦的家里了
back to your address in London.
-是吗   -特快专递
- Has he? -Special delivery.
你什么毛病啊 这太恶心了
What is the matter with you? That's really offensive.
你这样是歧视男人
Well, I think that's a bit sexist.
才没有 我为啥要用一根假JJ开车
No, it's not. Why would I want to drive with a rubber penis?
不知道啊 可能你是个变态
I don't know. I think you're weird.
休息结束 我们重新上路
With our break over, we got back on the road.
美国观众们 船长正开着一辆手动”屌”
For our American viewers, James May is driving a dick-shift.
而且不仅是船长的”裆把儿”
And it wasn't just James's knob
一直在逗我们笑
that was keeping us amused.
午餐的时候还听到一件事
There was something else we'd learned over lunch
更加好笑
that was even funnier.
船长的油箱上有个洞 或者是裂了
James May's fuel tank has a hole in it, or it's split.
他开的是一枚定时炸弹
He's driving a bomb.
现在形势很紧张
It's a tense moment, this.
就像足球赛快结束时比分1-1
It's like the end of a football match when it's 1-1.
你只管开 你知道他要炸
You're driving along, you know he's gonna blow up,
但是不知道啥时候炸
you just don't know when.
报纸登出来不好看吧
RICHARD: It's not gonna read well in the papers.
"詹姆斯梅死于沙滩车爆炸 手中握着假JJ"
"James May died in an exploding beach buggy, holding a rubber penis."
噢闭嘴吧
Oh, shut up!
我的天
Jeez!
正中面门
JAMES: Oh! In the face!
当船长的油箱见底时
JEREMY: Once James's fuel tank had run low enough,
我们停在了一个小村子里
we pulled over in a small village
他可以做些修补
so he could make some repairs.
因为风往那儿吹 所以爆炸的火球也朝那儿
Well, the wind's blowing that way, so the fireball will go up there.
等下他死的时候 一下子就完了
It'll be sudden, won't it, when he goes?
是啊 "轰"的一声
Yeah. It's "woompf."
然后一阵静寂
"Woompf," then a bit of quiet,
然后各种肉渣掉下来
and then... as all bits come down.
对
JEREMY: Yes.
油箱的裂缝在这里
Here's the split in the tank.
-用上这个  -你好
- Apply this. - Oh, hello!
你知道我们一直在说这路有多烂吧，哈蒙德
You know we've been saying how bad the roads are, Hammond?
嗯
Yes.
烂到能搞坏一辆搞不坏的车
They're bad enough to kill an un-killable car.
这场景也算可怕吧
That's kind of a terrifying sight, isn't it?
是啊 我这辈子从来没见过
I know. I've never seen that before in my life.
一辆报废的丰田皮卡
A dead Toyota pickup truck.
船长的油箱补好了
With James's tank bodged,
我们鼓足劲想多跑几里路
we knuckled down to getting some miles under our belt.
然而这天剩余时间里
And for the rest of the day,
唯一有燃料问题的人是我
the only person with petrol issues was me.
好了 加满了 我又能跑个50公里
Right. Refuelled, so I'm good now for 31 miles.
一天结束 我们有了不少进展
By the end of the day, we'd made good progress.
而当我们停下来扎营时
And when we stopped to make camp...
乔瓦尼他妈的去哪儿了
Where the bloody hell's Giovanni?
我们离终点只有不到160公里了
...we were less than 100 miles from the finish line.
所以晚饭后 我们决定讨论一番
So, after supper, we decided to have a conversation -
不对 争论一番
well, argument -
关于谁造的沙滩车最好
about who'd built the best beach buggy.
重点是 你造的不是沙滩车
The point is, yours isn't a beach buggy.
-我的车  -嗯
- My car? - Yeah.
我的车不仅有沙滩车的壳
Apart from having a beach buggy's body
还有一颗跳动的沙滩车之心
and the beating, pulsating heart of a beach buggy,
也就是甲壳虫的引擎
namely a Beetle engine.
我看着你的车就想
I look at yours and go,
"这看起来都不像一辆沙滩车"
"That doesn't even look like a beach buggy."
像啊 它就是沙滩车啊
It does and it is! It's a beach buggy.
这是升级版 但保留了沙滩车的灵魂
Enhanced, but in the spirit of beach buggying.
-根本不是  -杰里米 你的车是...怪物
- It isn't. - Jeremy, yours is... a freak.
如果在100年前 它会被拿去展览
Had it existed 100 years ago, it would have been exhibited.
人们会从大老远来围观 小孩子会透过帘子偷看
People would come from miles and children would peak at it through curtains.
"天呐 看那个怪兽"
"Oh, look at the monster!"
重点在于 我一直热爱
The point is, I have always loved
沙滩车的灵魂
the spirit of the beach buggy.
我热爱创造它的时代还有那个时代的一切
I love the era that created it and all of that.
但是有一件事我不喜欢
But the one thing that's made me not like it
这引擎让我想起希特勒
is the engine reminds me of Hitler.
我已经杀掉我体内所有希特勒的DNA了
I have removed all of that Hitler DNA from mine,
装了台超强的V8
fitted a bloody great V8.
它走火入魔了
It's gone too far.
-这是弗兰肯斯坦的车  -我来终结争论
- It's Frankenstein's buggy. - I can settle this.
-你的车不算是合格的沙滩车  -不算
- Yours isn't a proper beach buggy. - It isn't.
-但相比你更算是沙滩车  -扯淡
- But it's more of a beach buggy than yours. - Oh, rubbish!
因为沙滩车真正的灵魂
Because the true spirit of the beach buggy
就是甲壳虫的地板和引擎 他的车有
is the Beetle floorpan and engine, which his has.
你的车引擎都不过关
Yours doesn't have the engine.
而我的车啥都有
Mine actually has everything.
我的车才是合格的沙滩车
Mine is the proper beach buggy.
-抱歉 但是...  -你才不抱歉
- I'm sorry about this, James, but... - You're not.
你的车是放纵的60后造的
...your car was created
又被史蒂夫·麦奎因代言
by the swinging '60s and endorsed by Steve McQueen,
他是有史以来最酷炫的人
one of the coolest people who ever lived,
然而就算这样
and yet, somehow, you have managed
你都能把沙滩车变无聊
to make your beach buggy boring.
-扯淡  -是有一点
- Rubbish - It is a bit.
-它很没趣  -就像一场无聊的烟花秀
- It is boring. - It's a boring firework display.
-就是  -因为能正常运转才无聊
- It is. - It's boring in that it works.
-不 詹姆斯  -一点都不正常啊
- No, James. - It doesn't work!
唯一出的一点岔子
The only thing that has gone wrong
就是油箱的轻微渗漏
is a small leak in the petrol tank.
其他一切都保持正常工作
Everything else about it has constantly worked.
你知道吗 每次我超你的车
Do you know, every time I've overtaken you,
我看着你的车就想 "这太可怜了"
I've looked and thought, "That's dismal."
才不是 它有高贵而纯洁的血统
It isn't. It has an elegance and a purity.
你总是说 "你不可能超我的车"
And when you say, "You've never come past me,"
我每50公里就超你一次 因为你没油了
I come past you every 30 miles because you've run out of fuel.
这车前轮离地 油门卡住 电机脱落 螺丝失踪
It wheelies, the throttle sticks, the alternator falls off, bolts fall out of it.
-那电机...  -你得给它配个翼片 然后外观就毁了
- It... The alternator... - You've had to fit a wing on it, which ruins the looks.
这不是沙滩车的灵魂
It's not in the spirit of the beach buggy,
而是某人迫切想要维护一个糟糕的点子
but of a man desperately trying to justify a terrible idea.
-这是个绝佳的点子  -根本行不通啊
- It was a brilliant idea! - It doesn't work!
我现在注意到了
I'm fairly conscious right now
你的车在烧我车上的油
your car is drinking the fuel out of mine
就像一个塑料做的吸血鬼
like a sort of plastic vampire.
我的车很口渴
Look, mine has been thirsty.
-只是渴?  -对
- Thirsty? - Yes.
我们继续争论
JAMES: We continued arguing
直到乔瓦尼提醒我们该睡了
until Giovanni reminded us it was time to go to bed.
但我并没有睡
But I didn't go to bed,
因为我有事要做
because I had business to attend to.
杰里米觉得他很风光
Right, Jeremy Clarkson thinks he's being flamboyant,
但他不知道 我的空气动力学知识
and he doesn't realize that my knowledge of aerodynamics
比他往别人车上的装假JJ的能力强多了
will trump his ability to fit rubber penises to people's cars.
我擦
Shit!
哈蒙德 着火了
Hammond! Fire!
来人啊
Help!
哈蒙德 救火啊
Hammond! Help!
第二天早上 当我们继续前行
The next morning, as we resumed our journey,
我感觉看开了一切
I was feeling rather philosophical.
有一次我看见一位老太太摔倒
I once saw an old lady fall over
她的购物袋滚到路对面
and drop her shopping bag on the opposite side of the road,
买的东西都掉出来了
and her shopping fell out.
其中有一个复活节彩蛋
And amongst it was an Easter egg,
我猜是买给孙辈的
which I assume she bought for a grandchild or something,
彩蛋滚到了路中央 一辆车碾了过去
and it rolled into the road and got run over by a car.
这是我见过最悲惨的事情...
It was the most tragic thing I've ever seen...
直到今早我看见了我的车头
until I saw the front of my car this morning.
他毁掉的不仅仅是他自己的车头
And it wasn't just the front of his own car he'd ruined.
我是不介意 但是詹姆斯的成果抖的实在太吓人了
I wouldn't mind, but the rattling from James's workmanship is appalling.
尽管坎坷不断 但是我们快到了
Despite everything, though, we were now almost there.
今天我们就要到达代表着
Today, we would reach the beach that marked the finish
一段奇妙旅程的终点沙滩
of what had been a spectacular journey
穿越一个奇妙的国家
through a spectacular country.
真应该被戳一下
That deserves a stabbing.
我的天呐
RICHARD: Oh, my God!
哎我去
JEREMY: Oh, my...
乔瓦尼 你能准备下浴缸吗
Giovanni, could you run the baths?
来人啊
Help!
这实在是令人惊叹的一块地方
JEREMY: It really is an amazing part of the world, this.
但美妙背后是残酷
But everything that makes it amazing is harsh
无情而且艰难的环境
and unforgiving and difficult.
别抖了
Oh, stop!
从来没人这么说过 但是纳米比亚...
No one's ever said this before, but Namibia...
真他妈是个美丽的国家
...is a beautiful bastard of a country.
但是
And yet,
我们倒数旅程的最后几里路上
as we counted down the last few miles of our journey,
我们的自制沙滩车都还在跑
our home-made beach buggies were still running.
它们青一块紫一块 但是它们向制片人证明了
They were battered and bruised, but they'd proved our point to Mr Wilman.
它们成功了
They'd made it.
它们还完成了其他事
And they had done something else as well -
它们已经深入我心
they'd got under our skin.
比起一开始
We liked them even more at the end
现在我们更喜欢它们了
than we had done at the start.
我觉得世界上每个人都应该开一辆沙滩车
I think everybody in the world should drive a beach buggy,
因为你会直面更多的事物
because you're exposed to so much.
不仅仅是天地水土
Not just the elements,
还有其他人的态度
but the opinions of other people.
当你坐在普通的车里时
I mean, when you're in a normal car,
你挥拳头 摆手势
you shake your fist and make gestures,
你还大喊大叫
and shout and yell,
因为你觉得被包裹 很有安全感
because you feel cocooned and safe
对任何人都免疫
and immune from everybody.
但在沙滩车里 所有人就在面前
But in a beach buggy, everyone's just there.
这太棒了
It's brilliant!
这是一种友好的交通方式
It's such a friendly way of moving about.
怀着这种信念 我们一骑绝尘
And with that, we settled down
期待会有一条平坦的路通向海边
for what we hoped would be a smooth cruise to the beach.
然而并不是
But it wasn't.
天呐
Oh, God! Ow!
这太疯狂了
This is outrageous!
哎哟我去
Holy shit!
噢不 它彻底坏了
Oh, no! It's gone!
现在这车的空气动力性能大受影响
And now my aerodynamics are badly affected as well.
我勒个去
Oh, my word!
杰里米想就这样开到终点
Jeremy is hoping to get to the finish line
坐在一堆你所痛恨的邻居
in the sort of pile of scrap you hate your neighbors
会存在后院的那种破烂里
for keeping at the bottom of their garden.
要死要死
Oh, God!
噢不 油漏出来了
JEREMY: Oh, no! There's petrol!
哈蒙德 别靠近他的车
Oh! Hammond, don't go near his car!
他车头全是汽油
There's petrol all over the front of his car.
-是嘛  -真的
- Is there? - Yeah.
如果你着火了呢 詹姆斯
What if it caught fire, James?
只剩下最后48公里了
With just 30 miles to go,
强大的七缸V8真正开始玩大了
the mighty seven-cylinder V8 really started to play up.
哦不
- Oh, no!
然后天色渐渐暗了下来
And then it started to go dark,
带来一堆麻问题最大的问题
which presented us with the biggest problem of the lot.
太差劲了吧
That's just terrible.
哦天哪
Oh, God!
太棒了
Well, that's marvelous.
这个快要把我亮瞎了
That one is dazzling me
而那个闪成转向灯
and that one is showing me where to go.
这和想象中的差太远了
This is far from ideal.
在夜幕笼罩之前
Before pitch darkness fell,
我们停下车来做些紧急修理
we pulled over to do some emergency repairs.
我要用一些
I'm gonna put some...
某牌胶带来处理这个问题
tape of a certain well-known brand on the problem.
用手拧紧就可以了
Finger tight will do.
这些修理太成功了
These repairs were extremely successful.
哦 现在射到我脸上了
Oh, it's swung into my face!
不 我什么都看不见 比刚才还糟糕
No, I can't see a thing. Agh! That's worse!
我的亲娘 灯又歪另一边了
Oh, God. Now they've turned.
哦不 我的车又要斗鸡眼了
Oh, no! My car's gone cross-eyed again!
有个男的迎面驶来
There's a man coming the other way.
他会怎么想我们
What's he gonna think of us?
我不知道
I don't know.
我他妈什么都看不见
I can't see a bloody thing.
谢谢你 哦这很好
Thank you. Oh, that's good!
大灯又被晃到正面去了
It's shaken the headlight back round again!
耶 又转回来了 就那么一瞬间好好的
Yeah! No, it's back again. Oh, just for a moment.
这条起伏不平的路给前灯又带来了几个新问题
Then the rough road brought some new headlight problems.
哦什么都没了 没了
Oh, nothing! Oh, no! Nothing! Nothing!
我 我现在什么都没了
I've got... I've now got nothing at all.
好吧 哈蒙德还有梅 你们能不能告诉我
OK, Hammond and May, can you just let me know
你们现在的照明情况
what your lighting situation is now?
只要我抓着闪光灯控制杆 我就有光
As long as I hold the flash lever back, I have light.
如果我握着控制杆 一边是光 另一边闪光
If I hold the lever, I get one light and one flashing light, yes.
但是我要把手拿开去换档
But I have to take my hand off to change gear.
然后哈蒙德的车突然就变成了
And then Hammond's car suddenly turned into
平克弗洛伊德演出用的灯光设备
the lighting rig at a Pink Floyd gig.
为什么它一直在变 什么
Why does it keep changing? What...
乱套了
And it's all got...
现在只剩三公里了 三
It's only three kilometres to go now. Three.
他妈的啊
Oh, fucking hell!
没了 又亮了
Gone. Coming back.
虽然我们看不到
Although we couldn't see,
我们知道肯定离沙滩很近了
we knew we must be close to the beach.
这不是海边的沙滩
It's not... you know, a seaside beach.
肯定是在河流或者湖泊 或者别的什么
It must be on a river or a lake, or something.
只是个上坡 我敢确定这不对劲
This is uphill. I'm sure that's wrong.
这里真是个大下坡
That's a big drop there.
我可不想掉下去
I don't want to go off there.
我不确定这是否明智
I'm not sure this is sensible.
我读过的任何指南里都没有写
Nowhere in any guide I've ever read does it say,
在灯全坏的情况下 用沙滩车
"Explore new territory in a beach buggy
探索新的地域
with your lights all broken."
无法找到任何与沙滩有一点相近的地方
Unable to find anything even remotely resembling a beach,
我们停了下来
we pulled over.
我们不能在黑暗里继续这么跌跌撞撞前进
We cannot carry on just plunging around in the darkness,
希望能找到那个沙滩
hoping to find the beach.
而且 先不说这个 那是什么声音
And, anyway, what is that noise?
我会说… 是瀑布
I would say that...is a waterfall.
这是不是你想在黑暗中碰上的
Is it something you want to come across in the dark?
因为关于那个声音我还想说
Because the other thing I'd say about that sound -
可能我想多了 但感觉声音从脚下传来啊
it might be my imagination, but that sounds as though it's coming from below,
好像我们在瀑布之上
like we're above it.
我们从那个小道上爬上来
We have climbed up that track.
而瀑布本身定义就是悬崖
And a waterfall is a drop, by definition.
如果我们… 我可不想在黑夜里
If we're... I don't want to... in the dark.
放弃 我不干了
Abandon. I'm not doing it.
我们明天等太阳
We'll do it tomorrow. Sun.
让我们仰望星空 再在纳米比亚过一夜
Let's look at the stars and have one more night in Namibia.
我们明天会找到的 而且风景美不胜收
We'll find it tomorrow and it'll be fantastically glorious.
明天沙滩上见
RICHARD: Tomorrow on the beach.
乔瓦尼
JEREMY: Giovanni!
第二天早上 日光给我们揭晓了答案
The next morning, daylight brought answers to our questions.
所以它不是一条瀑布
So it wasn't a waterfall.
不 这是很多瀑布
No, it was many waterfalls.
数以百计的瀑布
Hundreds of waterfalls.
我们都赞同的一点就是
And they were just part of what we all agreed
这是我们见过最美的景色
was the most beautiful view we'd ever seen.
但是 很多瀑布
But...many waterfalls.
我看不到沙滩
No beach that I can see.
那个算沙滩吗
Does that count as a beach?
那就是沙滩
JEREMY: That is a beach.
我管那个叫沙滩
I'd call that a beach.
-沙滩 -肯定是了 没有别的了
- The beach. - That's got to be it. There's no others.
各位 我们的探索终于有了结果
Gentlemen, our quest is at an end.
让我们在这壮美中…
Let us ride...
驶去…
in splendour... to...
-结束语说的不好是不是 怎么讲 -很动人
- I'm not finishing that very well. What is it? - It's very moving.
我想说点引人共鸣的 古雅的佳句
I'm trying to think of something evocative and Victorian and brilliant.
不如说“咱们开到那边完事了吧”
How about “Let's go over there and finish our journey”?
不 那是粗人之语
No, that's Brummie rubbish!
－它是 -是大实话
- It is! - It's the fact.
无法找到合适的措辞来纪念这个时刻
Unable to find the right words to mark the moment...
我们还是出发了
...we set off anyway.
耶 就是这个
Yeah, this is it.
我们离我们的目标还有半公里
We are half a kilometre from our objective.
哦
Oh.
哦不 死路 死路
Oh, no. Path ends. Path ends.
额
Erm...
老天爷啊
Oh, my God!
好吧 如果这条路不通
Well, if this won't get over there,
他俩的路也不可能通
there's no way will theirs.
我们分头行动 寻找能够穿过石头的小路
We split up to look for a path through the rocks...
哦不
Oh, no!
但是毫无希望
...but it was hopeless.
算了吧
Forget it.
哈蒙德 算了吧
Hammond, forget it.
我们开不过这个土丘的
We aren't going down this hill.
问题是 就算我们可以越过这堆 更何况我们不能
The problem is, even if we could get over this stuff, which we can't...
不 我们做不到
RICHARD: No, we can't.
你们看到我们和沙滩中间是什么吗
...have you seen what's between us and the beach?
你看 绝对没办法可以开过或者开近
Look at it. There's no way you could drive over that or anywhere near.
-看 你甚至都不能到内陆 -不 我们过不去
- Look, you can't even go inland. - No, we can't go there.
而且你也不能绕过那个山
And you can't go around that mountain
然后从背面上来 因为都是悬崖
and come at it from the back, cos they're cliffs.
等等
Wait a minute.
什么
What?
我有
I've had...
一个好主意
...a great idea.
哦不 -不
- RICHARD: Oh, no. - No.
所以我们不能开到这里
So we can't drive over here.
但是我们必须本人和车到达沙滩
But we have to get us and our cars to that beach over there.
如果能有某种
If there were to be some kind of...
在那个悬崖上有个固定点
A mounting point on that cliff, maybe, and then--
干嘛
Do what?
不 那边建个固定点
No. Mounting point down there.
那种距离？这可是很长的距离
Over that distance? That's a huge distance.
-差不多有一里 -不
- It's about half a kilometre. - No!
但是你能想象它要承的力吗
But can you imagine the forces on it?
-固定物要很大才行 -很大
- The things at the end are gonna have to be... - Huge.
-巨大 -杰里米 我们并不都活在二次元里
- Massive. - Jeremy, we don't all live in a cartoon.
我们会死的 死翘翘
We will die! Dead!
考虑到没有别的选择了
Given that there were no alternatives,
我们只好听从大猩猩的计划
we had to go with the ape's plan,
也就是把我们的沙滩车变成缆车
which was to turn our beach buggies into cable cars.
-这个有两米多 -是的 足够好了
- That's over two metres. - Yeah, that's good enough.
所以我们前往附件一片废矿
So we headed to a nearby abandoned mine...
来寻找材料
...to scavenge materials.
这块能用吗
JAMES: Is that bit any good?
-我们还有多少缆索 -四盘
- How much more of that cable have we got? - Four drums.
-你是提议把它改造成缠索盘吗 -是的
- Are you proposing that that becomes a winding drum? - Yeah.
重要的是
It's very important...
我们要给哈蒙德的车加足重量
we get as much weight as possible into Hammond's car...
为了 好吧为了你们看乐呵
for erm... well, for your amusement.
好 工具箱
Right, toolbox.
-你需要多少 -30米
- JAMES: How much do you want? - JEREMY: 30 metres.
詹姆斯 那个圈你焊上了吗
James, have you got that hoop welded in yet?
没有 接下来要搞
No, that's my next job.
几天之后
Several days later,
在没有任何
and with absolutely no help whatsoever
纳米比亚采矿工程师的帮助下
from any Namibian mining engineers...
世界上第一辆沙滩缆车已经准备好了
...the world's first beach buggy cable car was ready, and--
卧槽 停 所有人
JEREMY: Shit! Stop, everybody!
山羊在吃这棵我们用来固定的树
The goats are eating the tree that we've anchored it to.
-嘘 山羊 -嘘
- Shoo, goats! Shoo!
它们在吃树
They were eating the tree.
不管怎样 正如我所说的
Anyway, as I was saying,
它长达一里
it stretched for more than a third of a mile.
而且几百米之下就是
And since the drop to the crocodile-infested river
满是鳄鱼的河流
was several hundred feet,
我们决定让詹姆斯先来
we decided James should go first.
-我们投票了 -真的吗
- We had a vote. - Did you?
是的 而且我们一致同意你第一个来
We did, and we were unanimous you were going first.
嗯 一下子变民主了是不是
Right, so it's become a democracy all of a sudden?
-是的 -没错
- JEREMY: Yes, it has. - Yeah.
而且不管怎么说 你的车是最轻的
And anyway, your car's the lightest,
因为你烧掉了一半
now you've burned half of it away.
我在爬上来 天啊
I'm climbing in. Jesus!
当最高端的发电机发动时
With the state-of-the-art generators fired up...
詹姆斯为了这个旅行壮胆
...James fortified himself for the journey...
他这是喝酒吗
Is he drinking?
然后就是开下发射台
...and then simply drove off the launch pad.
我滴妈啊
JAMES: Oh, my God! Whoa!
卧槽 这太高了
Oh, shit! It's really high!
这太高了 我要把引擎关了
It's really high! I'm turning the engine off.
-我们必须测试啊 -没错
- We had to test it. -Well, exactly.
-他必须第一个走 -不要看了以后觉得我们是坏人
- He had to go first. - Don't look at us and think we're bad.
因为这是为了保证科学
Because that was scientifically vigorous.
这是个缆车 这是个缆车
It's a cable car. It's a cable car.
我坐过很多缆车 它们很安全
I've been on lots of cable cars. They're safe.
-天哪快看他 这里是高的地方 -那太吓人了
-  God. Look, he's... This is where it's high. - RICHARD: That's horrible.
不 这太高了 我不喜欢
No! It's going really high! I don't like...
我恨你们
JAMES: I hate you!
-好吧 -他不喜欢我们
- OK. - He doesn't like us.
尽管我很恐慌 沙滩缆车依然缓缓前进
Despite my terror, the cable buggy kept on chugging through
越过了其实是安哥拉领空的地段
what's technically Angolan airspace towards the beach.
天哪 我快到了
God, I'm nearly there!
空挡 松手刹
Neutral. Handbrake off.
他就要做到了 他要做到了
He's gonna do it. He's gonna do it.
我到终点了
I'm at the end!
-他下去了 -安全降落
- He's down. - That's a landing.
耶
Yes!
-但是你知道吗 -什么
- Do you know what, though? - What?
-我在这里做了点算数 -嗯
- I'm doing maths here. - Mm?
很显然我们中有一个会死在这 对不对
One of us is gonna be killed doing this, obviously, yes?
-我也这么觉得 对 -所以我们都在这里的时候 33%的几率
- I'd say so, yeah. - So when we were all here, 33% chance.
现在 我要以50%的几率做这个
Now I'm doing it with a 50% chance.
-你现在倒抢着做了 -我要下一个
- Now you're doing it? - I'm going next.
-我要下一个来 -你不可以
- I can go next. - You can't go next.
为什么我不能下一个
- Why can't I go next? -
让詹姆斯喝更多的酒来庆祝成功时
Whilst James toasted his success with some more drink...
我赢得了这场争论 准备发射
...I won the argument and prepared for launch.
为什么我的车是这个角度、
Why is my car at this angle?
也许是因为有个巨大的V8悬挂在后面
Well, maybe because there's a massive V8 hanging out the back of it.
好吧 好好好
Right! Right, right, right!
我就… 出发吧
I'll... here we go.
我的直肠刚刚像剧院幕布那样打开
My rectum has just opened like a set of theatre curtains.
不是因为我怂 是因为我的沙滩车
And for good reason, because my beach buggy
比詹姆斯那烧焦了的残骸要重200公斤
weighed 200 kilograms more than James's charred wreck.
哦 他刮到草地了
Ooh! Ooh! He brushed the grass!
我很害怕 我说真的
I'm terrified, I'll be honest,
但是从我出发到现在
but, for the first time since I set off,
我第一次坐车里感到舒服
I'm comfortable in my beach buggy.
接近沙滩 接近这场旅程的终点
Approaching the beach. Approaching the end of the journey.
我到了
Here I come.
着地
And... touchdown!
耶
Yes!
坏消息 哈蒙德 我做到了
Bad news, Hammond. I've made it.
哦好吧
Oh, great.
-先生 -太客气了 詹姆斯
- Sir? - Oh, I say, James!
事实上 酒还有剩的算走运了
Actually, I was lucky there was some left,
因为当詹姆斯一个人的时候 他觉得有点口渴
because James had had a bit of a thirst on whilst he'd been alone.
你好 下面的伙计们
Hello, guys down there.
我是站在巅峰的理查德
It's Richard at the top.
好的 我现在要做这个了 所以再见
Right, I'm gonna do this now, so goodbye.
哦 我可不喜欢这个感觉
Oh! I don't like that feeling!
现在到来的是 女士们先生们 理查德哈蒙德
Here he comes, ladies and gentlemen, Richard Hammond.
不
No!
我可以安心的是
I could take solace from the fact that this system
这个系统已经测试过两次 成功两次 它是经过考验的
has already run twice with their cars and not failed - it's been tested.
或者我也可以更加现实一点
Or I could take a more realistic view,
那就是那两个肥仔已经把它变得脆弱
which is that those two fat oafs have already weakened it.
再加上他后面有一堆破铜烂铁
JEREMY: Plus he had all that scrap metal in the back,
这也是为什么所有的目光都注视着他
which is why all eyes were on him.
好吧 当我说“所有”目光的时候
Well, when I say "all"...
快看那边石头的颜色
Look at the colours in those rocks over there.
太美妙了
It's... It's fantastic.
就在哈蒙德的左边
Just to the left of where Hammond is.
为什么我的车这么低 它很重
Why's my car sitting so low? It is heavy.
它是 为什么它更低
It is... Why's it lower?
-那色彩不可思议不是吗 -是的
- The colouring is fabulous, isn't it? - Yeah, they are.
尽管我很害怕 缆索依然坚固
Despite all my fears, the cables were holding
而且拉着我越来越靠近另两位
and drawing me ever closer to my colleagues.
要成功了 我看到沙滩了
This is it. I can see the beach.
沙滩近在眼前 我们就要完成了
I'm so nearly there. We are gonna do it!
来吧哈蒙德 快来
Come on, Hammond. Come on.
我就要做到了
I'm gonna do it.
来吧哈蒙德 来吧
Come on, Hammond. Come on.
哦
Oh.
额
Erm...
为什么我停下来了
Why have I stopped?
-哈蒙德 -来啊
- Hammond! - Come on!
-我停住了 -哈蒙德
- I've stopped! -Hammond!
它就这么停住了
It's just stopped!
我能做什么  它停住了
What can I do? It's just stopped!
这里还有 大概 200米的距离
There's, like, 200 metres to go!
和我又没关系 又不是我说了算的
I don't have anything to do with it! It's not up to me!
你俩什么都做不了吗
Is there nothing you can do?
难过的是 詹姆斯醉的难以思考
Sadly, James was too drunk to think,
而我是个机械白痴
and I'm mechanically inept.
再加上 无论出什么问题 都是在那边顶端
Plus, whatever had gone wrong had gone wrong at the top,
而我们在底端
and we were at the bottom.
动啊 动啊
Move! Move! Move!
我们真的什么都做不了
There's literally nothing we can do.
我们考虑了各方面
We've assessed everything
你已经没救了
and you're in a hopeless position.
我们可以再喝瓶啤酒
We could have another beer.
我恐怕我们要下结论了
We've gonna have to conclude, I'm afraid,
制片人是对的 沙滩车并不好
that Mr Wilman was right that the beach buggy is no good.
伴随着这沮丧之情  是时候结束了
And on that terrible disappointment, it's time to end.
谢谢你们的观看 晚安
Thank you so much for watching. Good night.
BGM:You Got Your Head on Backwards by the Sonics